<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Leo Kuan – Communication</title>
    <link>/tags/communication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Communication on Leo Kuan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	  <atom:link href="/tags/communication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog: </title>
      <link>/blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;h1 id=&#34;leo-kuan&#34;&gt;Leo Kuan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;442-312-8828&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:me@leokuan.info&#34;&gt;me@leokuan.info&lt;/a&gt;
linkedin.com/in/leokuan
442-312-8828&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://leokuan.info&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/leokuan2021&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://linkedin.com/in/leokuan&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PAC Electric Co.
May 2015 to Present&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Manager
I have 8 years of PM experience managing simultaneous design-build and design-bid-build electrical and telecom construction projects from contract negotiation to project close-out. I manage cross-functional, remote and local teams of subcontractors, service vendors and material suppliers on a daily basis. I have managed infrastructure, industrial control and building projects up to $50M in scope, and have experience working with various agencies of the government at the city, state and federal level. I practice Continuous Improvement and try to introduce best practices to my team whenever possible, even ideas that may appear foreign to the construction industry. I am open to opportunities in the Software Development/IT industry and I am particularly interested in DevOps and Automation. I am open to relocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honolulu Rail Transit Project - City Center Utility Relocation III and III-E
May 2022 - Present
The electrical scope of the CCUR III project involves the construction and relocation of various dry utilities including power, telecom, cable, street lighting, traffic signal and intelligent transportation systems for the downtown segment of the bigger Honolulu Rail Transit project. The CCUR III-E is the electrification of the sub-transmission infrastructure to be constructed under CCUR III. Collectively this project is the largest project both PAC and myself have taken on to date. Project duration is roughly 2 years with an estimated cost of over $50M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Struck a deal with a CCTV Camera manufacturer and strategically disrupted a local monopoly of traffic monitoring CCTV cameras, leading to a $5M saving in costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coach and mentor project engineers. Share with personnel from the general contractor experience working with the same owner on a similar project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage field personnel, subcontractors and vendors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sand Island Wastewater Treatment Plant UV Channels Installation 3M
Jan 2021 - Present
Project description:
The UV Channels Installation is design-build retrofit project that involves the replacement of aging UV disinfection equipment in a critical facility. The project is cookie-cutter in nature with 5 similar phases but working with a major equipment vendor from overseas and the requirement to minimize downtime result in considerable complexity to the planning and execution of the build. The duration of the project is about 2 years and the estimated total cost for the electrical scope is $3M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Successfully convinced owner to accept the reuse of existing feeder cables, saving $200,000 in construction costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eliminated over-provisioned equipment in design and provided functionally equivalent alternative, saving $200,000 in construction costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convinced designers to eliminate excessive testing and studies requirements including the need for an independent third-party testing firm, saving $40,000 in costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fleshed out wanting construction drawings and transformed them into easy-to-follow drawings for field use, which led to precision execution of work plan in the field with no rework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feb 2021 - June 2021 &lt;br&gt;
Traffic Signal Controller and Central Management System Installation
Project description:
The scope of work includes surveying poorly-documented existing hardware in approximately 250 intersections, loading firmware to owner-purchased linux-based traffic controllers, installing a new central management system and maintaining all newly installed hardware for 3 years should anything malfunction. While I did not win the contract I was able to force a stalemate against competitors who were easily 10 times the size of my company and held a monopoly for decades in the state on similar projects. The estimated cost for the project was $12M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identified new business opportunity with high profit-margin potential and positioned company as a technology contractor to pursue said opportunity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimated project costs, formed and led an RFP response team consisting of mainland and local consultants, engineers, vendors and technical writers. Led system demo session and panel discussions for Hawaii DOT as one of three finalists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Successfully protested bid result to prevent contract from being awarded to competitors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrated leadership capability to business partners and solidified relationships. New relationships formed with vendors and experience gained later contributed to the cost savings of $5M on another project one year later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019 – 2020    University of Hawaii West Oahu Creative Media Facility
The Creative Media Facility is a new state-of-the-art educational facility for the University of Hawaii West Oahu with a university-scale server room, fiber connections throughout, and specialty rooms geared for various media production. The design-build nature of the project afforded quite a few opportunities to value-engineer, but it was apparent from the beginning the project was underestimated and quickly became an uphill battle with damage control being the central theme. The duration for the project was 18 months and the estimated cost was $4.5M&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value-engineered every aspect of this state-of-the-art educational facility project and obtained approval for atypical materials and systems which resulted in a 5% reduction in overall costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategically delayed procurement of the high-cost technical lighting materials and successfully convinced designers to accept fewer quantities than originally required by contract, saving $100,000 in construction costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Led coordination meetings involving multiple disciplines including electrical, telecom, AV, stage lighting, architectural lighting, fire alarm and security to resolve design and constructability issues. Meticulously version-controlled construction plans to avoid rework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saved approximately $30,000 in costs by eliminating the need for start-up services of a security subcontractor; Personally configured new emergency phones and integrated with the university&amp;rsquo;s existing VoIP system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintained team morale through communication, one-on-one interaction, coaching and mentoring despite former foreman&amp;rsquo;s abrupt departure mid-project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2018 – 2020    Waianae Wastewater Treatment Plant Electrical Improvements&lt;br&gt;
The Waianae WWTP Electrical Improvements project was an electrical upgrade project that involved replacing MCCs, PLCs and control instruments at about 10 different locations within the same plant. The critical nature of the facility and requirement to minimize downtime, as well as coordination with concurrent projects made phasing extremely difficult. The duration of the project was 2 years and the estimated cost was $3M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constant personnel change on the general contractor’s team as well as the owner&amp;rsquo;s team provided an opportunity for me to step up and provide much needed stability and continuity to the project where I was able to provide guidance and recommendation to less experienced project personnel from the GC team and facilitate negotiation with the owner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Planned and executed a recovery plan for key equipment suffering from a catastrophic failure that only required a negligible amount of additional labor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Led all start-up activities in the field and saved the costs for a system integrator. Worked with application engineers from equipment manufacturers to configure field devices remotely to shorten construction durations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-engineered and executed a phasing plan that saved approximately $200,000 in equipment rental costs while minimizing impacts to the plant&amp;rsquo;s normal operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2015 – 2017    Honolulu Rail Transit Project - West Oahu and Farrington Guideway Utility Relocation
I led this design-build infrastructure mega project after the departure of several project managers within a short amount of time. This was the first phase of the Honolulu Rail Transit project which involved the construction and relocation of various dry utilities including power, telecom, cable, street lighting, traffic signal and intelligent transportation systems, among other things. This was one of the company’s most successful projects and brought in $3M of profit. The duration of the project was 3 years and the estimated cost was $17M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accurately tracked a very large volume of change work with document backup that led to successful cost recovery and negotiations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coached and mentored a team of 12 team members in the field, resulting in greater productivity and efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduced a Kanban board to field personnel to enable better planning of day-to-day work with different levels of priorities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created and executed work plans for difficult installations, and did it with a crew with no prior experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;2014&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Master of Science, Electrical Engineering, Computer and Networking Focus&lt;/strong&gt;; University of Hawaii at Manoa&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;2006&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bachelor of Science, Electrical Engineering, Computer and Networking Focus&lt;/strong&gt;; University of Hawaii at Manoa&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;certification&#34;&gt;Certification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Certified Kubernetes Administrator (CKA)&lt;/strong&gt; January 23, 2022&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;AWS Certified Solutions Architect - Associate (SAA)&lt;/strong&gt; December 05, 2021&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
